Guide to the Henry M. Lyons Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry M. Lyons papers
1893-1948
1900-1901
MS 1572
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of correspondence, a diary, and memorabilia of Henry M. Lyons, a private in the British Royal Army Medical Corps, 10th Bearer Company, 12th Brigade, during the Boer War. Lyons recounts his experiences as a stretcher bearer and his impressions of camp life, the Boers, numerous skirmishes, and the weather and terrain of South Africa. Memorabilia includes his medical kit and a letter of a captured Boer. A small amount of correspondence from his military service in France during World War I is also included in the papers.
Lyons, Henry M.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator, 2001.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, a diary, and memorabilia of Henry M. Lyons, a private in the British Royal Army Medical Corps, 10th Bearer Company, 12th Brigade, during the Boer War. Lyons recounts his experiences as a stretcher bearer and his impressions of camp life, the Boers, numerous skirmishes, and the weather and terrain of South Africa. Memorabilia includes his medical kit and a letter of a captured Boer. A small amount of correspondence from his military service in France during World War I is also included in the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
South African War, 1899-1902 -- Personal narratives; South African War, 1899-1902; South Africa -- History -- 1836-1909; Lyons, Henry M.
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - From Sallie Lyons (wife), 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Sallie Lyons
      - 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1901, ca.1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1915, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1900 September-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia
    - Life assurance, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letter captured from a Boer, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Military dispatch, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Remittance, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Medical kit, pouch, Circa1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Red Cross patches, Circa1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous [clippings, poem, list of medals], 1939, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photograph, [191?] (Box 1, Folder 14)